<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Posts on That Crazy Webdev</title><link>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/</link><description>Read the latest Posts on That Crazy Webdev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 16:27:18 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Show XYZ: neopub</title><link>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/show-xyz-neopub/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 16:27:18 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/show-xyz-neopub/</guid><description>This description from the IndieWeb wiki describes best what neopub is1. I built neopub as because I wanted to have a micropub endpoint to be able to like stuff in monocle, post from Micro.blog and because I like doing hard things.
neopub is a blogging software developed by RobinBoers. It runs micro.geheimesite.nl and is written in PHP. It has a built-in micropub endpoint and sends webmentions. neopub is inspired by neofeed, publog and aaronparecki.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This description from the IndieWeb wiki describes best what neopub is<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. I built neopub as because I wanted to have a micropub endpoint to be able to like stuff in <a href="https://monocle.p3k.io">monocle</a>, post from <a href="https://micro.blog">Micro.blog</a> and because I like doing hard things.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em><strong>neopub</strong> is a blogging software developed by <a href="https://indieweb.org/User:Geheimesite.nl">RobinBoers</a>. It runs <a href="https://micro.geheimesite.nl">micro.geheimesite.nl</a> and is written in PHP. It has a built-in micropub endpoint and sends webmentions. neopub is inspired by <a href="https://github.com/victoriadrake/neofeed-theme">neofeed</a>, <a href="https://p83.nl">publog</a> and <a href="https://aaronparecki.com">aaronparecki.com</a>.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>~ <a href="https://indieweb.org/neopub">https://indieweb.org/neopub</a></p>
<p>If you want to learn more about neopub, check the IndieWeb wiki. This post is about how and why I made it.</p>
<p>I wanted to set up some sort of micropub endpoint since I saw <a href="https://neofeed.dev">neofeed</a> while building this blog. Recently I came across <a href="https://p83.nl">p83.nl</a> when trying to export my subscriptions from aperture. It&rsquo;s a website built by Peter Stuifzand. I felt really inspired by the design<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> and the fact that he built his own blogging software<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> to run the thing.</p>
<p>So I started working on my own thingie. I decided to use PHP because I can run PHP applications on my webserver without the need for an external server/VPS. I found <a href="https://gist.github.com/adactio/8168e6b78da7b16a4644">this minimal micropub endpoint</a> by <a href="https://adactio.com">Jeremy Keith</a> and editted it with a bit of help from the IndieWeb wiki to write posts to a file: <code>feed.json</code>.</p>
<p>In neopub, all posts are written to a JSON file in the content directory. Every year a new JSON file is created, so after a few years of use you&rsquo;ll have something like this in the content directory:</p>
<ul>
<li>2022.json</li>
<li>2023.json</li>
<li>2024.json</li>
<li>etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>At most I post once per two days, some weeks once a day. That means that in one year I accumulate around 250-300 posts. I think the server will be able to handle rendering that, so I&rsquo;m not really woried about performance.</p>
<p>On the pages for tags or post types only posts from the current year are visible. I wanted older posts to be hidden by default. You can of course still access them via their permalink or using for example: <a href="https://micro.geheimesite.nl/posts/2021">https://micro.geheimesite.nl/posts/2021</a><sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.</p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/RobinBoers/neopub/master/screenshot.png" alt="Screenshot">
<em>Screenshot of the homepage of my microblog running neopub</em></p>
<p>That&rsquo;s about it. I&rsquo;m planning on adding some more features, like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Being able to change/delete posts</li>
<li>A media endpoint for uploading photos</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want you can find the source code <a href="https://github.com/RobinBoers/neopub">on GitHub</a></p>
<p><em>This was also posted to
<a href="https://indieweb.xyz/en/indieweb" class="u-syndication">/en/indieweb</a>.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>It&rsquo;s almost like I wrote it :D&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>You can definitely see that in the final design of neopub&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>It&rsquo;s called <a href="https://p83.nl/projects/publog">publog</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>I just started posting this year, so this page is empty, but you get the point.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Going IndieWeb</title><link>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/going-indieweb/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 13:06:12 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/going-indieweb/</guid><description>I recently moved this blog and its big dutch brother to my own site. I did this because I wanted to be in control of my content (and more importantly, its URL) and because I like to do hard stuff I guess. This blog is now hosted as a git repository over on GitHub, which means I can use version control. I can also host it using GitHub pages and deploy it using GitHub actions, which is pretty neat.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I recently moved this blog and <a href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl">its big dutch brother</a> to my own site. I did this because I wanted to be in control of my content (and more importantly, its URL) and because I like to do hard stuff I guess. This blog is now hosted as a git repository <a href="https://github.com/RobinBoers/blog">over on GitHub</a>, which means I can use version control. I can also host it using GitHub pages and deploy it using GitHub actions, which is pretty neat.</p>
<p>This was the first step in <a href="https://indiewebify.me">indiewebifying</a> my website. I also set up <a href="https://indieweb.org/IndieAuth">IndieAuth</a>, <a href="https://indieweb.org/h-card">h-card</a>, I marked my posts up using <a href="https://microformats.io">microformats2</a> and I started sending <a href="https://webmention.net">webmentions</a>.</p>
<p>So, what is this <a href="https://indieweb.org">IndieWeb</a>? Well, technically it is just a collection of APIs, guidelines, and principles to allow websites to interact with each other. It is about owning your online identity and content. Instead of being reliant on <a href="https://indieweb.org/silo">silos</a> like Facebook, Blogger, Instagram, or Twitter you self-host all of your content and optionally syndicate it to other platforms.</p>
<p>For example, if I wanted to tweet something<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> I would publish the tweet <a href="https://micro.geheimesite.nl">on my own site</a> and then syndicate it to Twitter using <a href="https://brid.gy">Brid.gy</a><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. When people then reply to me on Twitter, those replies would get sent to my website using webmentions, so that I can show those comments on my site.</p>
<p>But it gets even better than just replies from Twitter. I can send webmentions to other IndieWeb sites, where they then show up under their posts, and when other sites send me webmentions I can display them below my posts.</p>
<p>I can now also sign in using my domain name (on websites that support IndieAuth<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>) instead of creating an account or using &ldquo;Sign in with Google/Facebook&rdquo;. My profile data, like profile picture, bio and name are saved on my website using an <a href="https://indiewebify.me/validate-h-card?url=https://geheimesite.nl">h-card</a>. It&rsquo;s like Gravatar, but better.</p>
<p>When I publish a post on this blog now, it gets scanned by <a href="https://webmention.app">webmention.app</a> and webmentions will be sent to all URLs in this post, telling them I mentioned them. When people respond to this post I&rsquo;ll get a webmention and I can then render the reply below my posts.</p>
<p>But it gets even better. I have also moved <a href="https://micro.geheimesite.nl">my notes</a> from this blog to a separate microblog running <a href="https://indieweb.org/neopub">neopub</a>, a blogging software with a <a href="https://indieweb.org/micropub">micropub endpoint</a> that I built, and I moved my Inoreader subscriptions to <a href="https://aperture.p3k.io">aperture</a>. I can now comment on articles in my RSS reader and those comments will be published on my site, after which I can then send webmentions to the article. Pretty cool right?</p>
<p><em>This was also posted to
<a href="https://indieweb.xyz/en/indieweb" class="u-syndication">/en/indieweb</a>.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I don&rsquo;t use Twitter, but just imagine I did for a second.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I already syndicate posts from my dutch blog to LinkedIn.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Which is mostly other IndieWeb sites or services, but in the future hopefully more sites will support it (maybe?)&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>A phoneless month.</title><link>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/a-phoneless-month/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 12:54:39 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/a-phoneless-month/</guid><description>February was a special month for me. I had challenged myself to put away my phone for an entire month. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share my experience.
But, why would I want to do this? I found myself glued to my phone a lot lately. At home, when I woke up, in the evening, at school, and even on the toilet. In addition, I also noticed it was annoying me everyone expects you to always be available.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>February was a special month for me. I had challenged myself to put away my phone for an entire month. In this post, I&rsquo;d like to share my experience.</p>
<p>But, why would I want to do this? I found myself glued to my phone a lot lately. At home, when I woke up, in the evening, at school, and even on the toilet. In addition, I also noticed it was annoying me everyone expects you to always be available.</p>
<p>So, how&rsquo;d it go? I have to say I quite enjoyed the peace it gave me, however, I was counting down in the last week. And in free periods and breaks at school, when all my friends were playing games without me, I did miss my phone a bit. But I also liked to not be distracted the whole time, and it also motivated me to think of other ways to spend my time when I was bored. I finished three books in the first week alone in just the breaks at school.</p>
<p>There were a few problems tho. My school is in Schiedam, and I always make my homework together with my best friend Kevin, but calling is quite hard without a phone. Discord for the rescue, but it just isn&rsquo;t as practical as Whatsapp is. My school schedule is also on my phone, and it just isn&rsquo;t feasible to start my computer every morning at 6 o&rsquo;clock. Which means I was too early at school five times.</p>
<p>I do realize now that with exception of some really important communication my phone isn&rsquo;t that important at all. I deleted YouTube and Reddit straight away, and those apps aren&rsquo;t coming back (ever).</p>
<p>It is a bit strange that we always have to be available. Instant messaging is cool and all because it allows you to have conversations over great distances, but it also creates the expectation that you&rsquo;ll respond to every message straight away.</p>
<p>Maybe people will tell me that to use my laptop for school and work is cheating. But that is like saying eating vegetables when you&rsquo;re trying to eat no sugar is cheating. The goal wasn&rsquo;t to completely get rid of devices or to cut me from all communications. I just wanted to experience what it is like to not be available at any time of the day and to find alternative ways to spend my time. Besides, it was also interesting to see how this would affect my social life.</p>
<p>Conclusion? It was certainly an informative experience. I don&rsquo;t know if I would recommend it, but if you feel inspired I would encourage you to try it.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Distros DO NOT matter. Get over it.</title><link>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/distros-do-not-matter-get-over-it/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 12:09:42 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/distros-do-not-matter-get-over-it/</guid><description>I have been asked many times &amp;ldquo;what is the best distro for gamers&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;which linux distro should I pick&amp;rdquo;. There is this huge misconception in people&amp;rsquo;s minds that some Linux distros are better than others, that they have to pick the right one. The truth is, all distros are fundamentally the same. There is no such thing as &amp;rsquo;the best Linux distro'.
Most Linux beginners download a lot of ISO images and judge the distros on their look, preinstalled apps, and desktop environment.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I have been asked many times &ldquo;what is the best distro for gamers&rdquo; or &ldquo;which linux distro should I pick&rdquo;. There is this huge misconception in people&rsquo;s minds that some Linux distros are better than others, that they have to pick the right one. The truth is, all distros are fundamentally the same. There is no such thing as &rsquo;the best Linux distro'.</p>
<p>Most Linux beginners download a lot of ISO images and judge the distros on their look, preinstalled apps, and desktop environment. To be frankly honest, I did the same thing when I started with Linux. But it is the equivalent of going to a computer store and choosing a laptop based on its default wallpaper.</p>
<p>To understand this you need to look at what a distro even is. A distro is a set of packages. You might have heard this joke:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What you guys are referring to as Linux, is in fact, GNU/Linux, or as I&rsquo;ve recently taken to calling it, GNU plus Linux. Linux is not an operating system unto itself, but rather another free component of a fully functioning GNU system made useful by the GNU corelibs, shell utilities and vital system components comprising a full OS as defined by POSIX.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That is because Linux is the kernel. The kernel is a piece of software that acts as a layer between the software and hardware. But with only a kernel you can&rsquo;t run applications, play fancy games, or even have simple shapes on screen. We need other software for that: Xorg or Wayland for the display, PulseAudio or ALSA for the audio, and NetworkManager for wifi to name a few.</p>
<p>A Linux distro is a set of packages to provide you with everything you need. But most of the time distros use the exact same packages. And preinstalled themes or applications can be easily changed within a few minutes.</p>
<p>So, what purpose do distros serve? Most of the differences between distros are their software repositories. That is the spot where they get their software from. Arch Linux, for example, has newer packages than Debian. That means your apps will be updated more frequently, but the chance of unstable software is also greater.</p>
<p>For new beginners, the only thing that truly matters is the desktop environment. That is the way the UI looks. I do not mean themes, they&rsquo;re about colors and can be effortlessly changed. No, desktop environments are about the system UI. The panels, system applications, and applets. They are what end-users really need to worry about. For each major desktop environment, I picked a Linux distro that ships it preinstalled. Take a look at <a href="https://gist.github.com/RobinBoers/27235ffe97d4f38c880773dc899545d7">the list</a>!</p>
<p>Some readers might notice I didn&rsquo;t mention Ubuntu at all. That is because I think their UI is confusing for beginners, and I don&rsquo;t like the direction the distro is going. It also doesn&rsquo;t offer a better experience than vanilla GNOME, and I don&rsquo;t like how they&rsquo;re trying to push snaps down your throat.</p>
<p>I hope this post will help some people. I&rsquo;m open to debate if you think differently about this topic. Let me know in the comments!</p>
<p>Cheers!
Robin</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Plans and projects for 2022</title><link>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/plans-and-projects-for-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 09:09:26 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/plans-and-projects-for-2022/</guid><description>Just like last year I&amp;rsquo;m writing about my goals and projects I want to complete this year. But first, how did I do last year? Well, in this post I wrote about my progress in 2021. Quick recap:
I wanted to learn Express (servers) I wanted to build GTK+ apps I wanted to learn React to build mobile apps with React Native I wanted to create 3D games and prototypes using Three.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Just like <a href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl/2021/01/dit-wil-ik-leren-in-2021.html">last year</a> I&rsquo;m writing about my goals and projects I want to complete this year. But first, how did I do last year? Well, in <a href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl/2021/07/waar-ben-ik-momenteel-in-mijn-plannen.html">this post</a> I wrote about my progress in 2021. Quick recap:</p>
<ul>
<li>I wanted to learn Express (servers)</li>
<li>I wanted to build GTK+ apps</li>
<li>I wanted to learn React to build mobile apps with React Native</li>
<li>I wanted to create 3D games and prototypes using Three.js</li>
</ul>
<p>So, did I accomplish these goals? Well, sorta. I didn&rsquo;t do anything with GTK. Mostly because the docs suck, and for Node.js they are even worse. I might try <a href="https://valadoc.org/granite/Granite.html">Granite</a> in the future. Who knows? But GTK and Linux deserve a whole post on their own.</p>
<p>I also got a bit distracted by <a href="https://svelte.dev/">Svelte</a>, and I <a href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl/2021/08/hallo-svelte.html">wrote a little app</a> using Svelte instead of learning React as I planned. I still want to learn React because I like the idea to write iOS and Android apps using React Native. I recently saw <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kbhl379x1cw">this talk</a> about integrating React Native with <a href="https://www.phoenixframework.org">Phoenix Framework</a>, which sounds cool.</p>
<p>I totally forgot Express to be honest. That may also illustrate how much I was actually interested in it.</p>
<p>But to end on a positive note: I&rsquo;ve got a job at <a href="https://qdentity.nl">Qdentity</a> since September 2021. I mentioned Phoenix Framework earlier in this post, and that is because that is what they use at Qdentity. So I&rsquo;m learning <a href="https://elixir-lang.org">Elixir</a> and Phoenix now. Phoenix is a framework to build interactive websites and web apps in Elixir. You&rsquo;ll hear me talk about it a lot more this year, so be prepared :)</p>
<p>Oh, I almost forgot: my plans for this year. I already mentioned Phoenix and Elixir, but I&rsquo;m also still interested in React and React Native. Also cool: I&rsquo;ve got a new app I&rsquo;m working on. It&rsquo;s called Nindo and I used it to publish this post before I transfered it to my own blog.</p>
<p>Happy new year everyone!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Hi, I'm that Crazy Webdev!</title><link>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/im-that-crazy-webdev/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 10:35:23 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/post/im-that-crazy-webdev/</guid><description>Hi! My name is Robin. I&amp;rsquo;m an enthusiastic developer from the Netherlands. I&amp;rsquo;m also the creator of Nindo, and this is my third blog. For dutch people, I also have a blog over here: Webdevelopment-En-Meer. If you want to know more about me, check my personal website. And for English readers, I also have a second blog where I post about solutions for stupid problems, creatively titled, Stupid Codes.
Enough about me, what&amp;rsquo;s this new blog all about?</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hi! My name is Robin. I&rsquo;m an enthusiastic developer from the Netherlands. I&rsquo;m also the creator of Nindo, and this is my third blog. For dutch people, I also have a  blog over here: <a href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl">Webdevelopment-En-Meer</a>. If you want to know more about me, check my <a href="https://geheimesite.nl">personal website</a>. And for English readers, I also have a second blog where I post about solutions for stupid problems, creatively titled, <a href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl/notes">Stupid Codes</a>.</p>
<p>Enough about me, what&rsquo;s this new blog all about? Well, like I said before, I already have a dutch blog where I regularly post about programming and my other hobbies. This blog is an attempt to reach a broader audience for my posts.</p>
<p>So what kind of posts can you expect? I mostly talk about programming and new stuff I learn, but also about software-development as a whole. I&rsquo;m also a Linux enthusiast, so you&rsquo;ll also see me talk about Linux and open-source in general a lot.</p>
<p>So, if you&rsquo;re interested you can follow me <a href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/index.xml">via RSS</a> or via <a href="https://follow.it/crazy-webdev-s-feed-nindo?action=followPub">follow.it</a></p>
<p>And then I will see you again when I post my very creative and fun posts :)</p>
<p>- Robin</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>